http://youtu.be/EzXcbvVfFOk
http://youtu.be/EzXcbvVfFOk
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So let's take a look
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Bây giờ bắt đầu từ
at how we can use a data sheet to clarify information
làm cách nào dùng data sheet để tìm thông tin
on registers in our program.
của những thanh ghi trong program của bạn.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Because sometimes we give you code
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Bởi vì đôi lúc chúng tôi đưa code cho bạn
and you may not understand it.
nhưng bạn không hiểu nó viết gì.
So let's look up this register here.
Thì hãy nhìn vào thanh ghi này.
So I copied this register.
Tôi copy thanh ghi này.
Let's see if we can look it up in the data sheet.
Coi thử bạn có tìm thấy thông tin nào về nó trong data sheet không
So here's our data sheet for the TM4C123 microcontroller.
Đây là data sheet của vi điều khiển TM4C123.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So let's try to find what we are looking for.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Xem thử ta tìm được gì.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: All right so I'm going to do Control F,
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Tôi bấm Ctrl + F
and down here I'm going to type in the register I'm looking for.
ở đây, tôi đánh vào thanh ghi tôi đang tìm
Unfortunately, the syntax is such that we're not going to find that.
Đen rồi, ngữ cảnh không đúng, ta không tìm thấy gì đâu.
And that's because, in the data sheet, it doesn't call it by the underlines.
Bởi vì trong data sheet, nó xài tên kiểu khác
It doesn't use the underlines.
Nó không xài dấu gạch nối.
So in order to look up a register with find,
Cho nên để tìm thanh ghi này,
we're going to have to talk data sheet language.
ta phải làm giống nó.
And that is the RCGC2 register without the underlines.
Đây là thanh ghi RCGC2, không có gạch nối.
So we can search for it.
Giờ thì mới tìm ra.
Now there's a lot of them.
Hơi bị nhiều.
This found it in the table of contents.
Trong mục lục.
So that's pretty good, at the table of contents,
Tốt rồi, trong mục lục,
I'm just going to click right here.
Click vào đây.
And there we are.
Tìm thấy rồi.
This is the run mode clock gating control register 2.
Đây là thanh ghi điều khiển clock gating số 2 ở chế độ hoạt động, run mode, bình thường.
And if we scroll down we can see that the particular pin that we were turning
Nếu ta cuộn xuống sẽ thấy chân nào sẽ được bật
on was bit 5 to turn on Port F. So again,
khi set bit số 5, đó là port F.
if you're going to search the data sheet make sure you don't use the underlines.
Nhắc lại, nếu bạn tìm trong data sheet, đừng xài dấu gạch nối.
And so you can see that this register is defined just with the letters
Bạn sẽ thấy thanh ghi được đặt tên bằng ký tự
and not with the underlines.
mà không có dấu gạch nối.
All right, don't be afraid of the data sheet.
Và đừng sợ data sheet.
It has lots of information.
Tuy là nó có quá nhiều thông tin.